Good morning everyone. Can you hear me?
[clears throat]
>> Yes.
>> Yeah, we can hear you.
>> Good afternoon, Prof. We can hear you.
Can
>> we wait a few seconds before we begin?
All right, it's 8 in the morning. Good
morning everybody and welcome to the
spring 2026 edition of uh introduction
to deep learning.
So by now if you've been uh you should
all have been signed on to Piaza.
You should have seen a logistics post on
Piaza. There's a lecture zero about
logistics that has been posted on the
course website. So you should have
watched it. There are a number of
recitation zeros which are background
material for the course. You should have
at least have uh looked through those if
not if not watched some of them. You
should have been to the course website.
The course website is
deeplearning.cs.cmu.edu.
If you've not been there, please visit
it at once. Uh course objectives,
logistics, quiz and homework policies,
grading policies, all of these are both
in the logistics lecture and on the
course page. So please familiarize
yourself with this information.
Also again as I mentioned, you should be
signed on to Piaza.
You should all have been added to Canvas
and AutoLab. Please verify that you have
access to them. If you don't, post on
Piaza and our TTAs will take care of it
for you. You must also have seen the
note on forming study groups. So, we
recommend that students form study
groups and work in teams because you
work better in teams than you do by
yourself. So, sign up for the study
groups as soon as you can.
Third, our course philosophy is to leave
no student behind. Now, it's a tough
course. You're going to have to work
very hard to get your A. But in our
ideal world, every one of you would earn
an A. And historically, about 70% of
students in the course get some version
of an A. But it's not not an easy grade.
You work for it, but then we support you
and we provide lots of resources for it.
We have an army of TAs. We form you into
study groups. Study groups are assigned
TA mentors. We encourage collaboration.
We hold uh over 50 office hours every
week. I'm always available. You can
email me and if I'm in Pittsburgh, you
can just walk into my office. You're
allowed to discuss and collaborate with
your friends and classmates.
Also, the course is tough, but then
you're also in the midst of going to be
in the midst of a tough semester. So,
some of you will find yourself under
stress or unable to perform. If that
happens, we have assigned some TAs
specifically to deal with cases like
these. So, reach out to your TA mentor,
reach out to this team or to me and and
we'll do our best to help you.
Now, we really really encourage
teamwork. So on Saturday the 17th we
have a meet and greet plus a lab and a
hackathon. There will be posts about it.
That's where you meet your colleagues,
you make some friends and collaborators,
you form study groups and if you already
have a study group come as a group.
You're going to learn how to get started
with deep learning code and uh well
there will be pizza.
So I must mention that in this first
week because next Monday is a holiday.
So in this first week we'll have three
lectures Monday, Wednesday and Friday so
that we stay on top of the calendar and
uh so the lab for this week will be on
Saturday along with a hackathon.
Our course objectives is that by the end
of the course you will all be able to
understand some of the theory behind
neural networks to be able to build your
own neural network components and tools
and to be able to work on large scale
problems. So the first point
understanding [clears throat]
some of the theory behind neural
networks you will hopefully know some of
the what the why and the how. You'll
understand some of the math. You'll
provide some of the occasionally provide
some history. And this will help you
contextualize bullets two and three
below. Namely that you will be able to
build your own neural network components
and tools and you'll be able to work on
large scale problems.
So also understanding the theory
will help you develop and extend your
own ideas on the topic. This will help
you in your research, will help you in
your grad school applications and with
job interviews.
Also, by the end of the course, you
should be able to build your own neural
network components and tools. So, these
are part ones of your homeworks and the
homeworks also have various bonus
problems. So, uh working on those will
also give you a much firmer uh grounding
and how neural networks work and how you
can build build your tools yourself.
The uh third part of the course is where
you work on large scale problems. These
are part twos of your homeworks where
you'll be competing with each other on
Kaggle on state-of-the-art tasks. So
between these it's going to be a lot of
work but by the end of the semester you
will probably find if you stay with us
you'll probably find that you have
learned more over this 3-month period
than you did in any other 3-month period
of your life.
Some of you will have course projects.
Those who are in 685 or 785
and course projects may relate to any of
these three bullets.
My lecture style it's very
I use lots and lots of visualization. I
use many many slides. I animate stuff
given a choice between deriving an
equation symbolically and explaining it
with 30 slides of pictures and
animation. I usually prefer the visual
uh the visual presentation with pictures
and animation. If this is not the kind
of lecture that you like then this might
not be the class for you.
We want you to attend all the lectures
because you learn,
but you kids will be overwhelmed with
all that's going on in the semester. And
so there is the temptation to maybe skip
class when you can just get away with
it. And we know that's not a great
thing. So we have different ways of
tracking your attendance. you get points
for attendance and we will use in-class
polls for class particip participation
to ensure that you're there. There will
be multiple polls posted at random times
through the class for in-class lectures
where I'm holding the class in
Pittsburgh. The polls will be posted on
piaza. So the piaza post numbers for the
polls will be called out in class and uh
you should keep your piaza open. Then we
have lectures on zoom like we do today.
Then we have zoom polls and you must
respond to all polls. We don't score you
on correctness. We check if you've
responded and we determine if you
attended the lecture based on whether
you show up whether and whether you
responded to post.
Now, some students are in really bad
time zones and attending this lecture is
going to be hard, especially if you're
in the Silicon Valley where it's 5:30
5:00 a.m. right now. So, for these
students and these students alone and
for any other students who have received
special permission, we allow you we
allow you to watch MediaTek videos. All
of the lectures are recorded. The
recorded lectures go up on media media
tech and on YouTube. Links to these
recordings will be posted on the course
page and as it happens, MediaTek records
who has watched the lecture and for how
long and at what rate. So we can gather
all of this information from there and
we will use that to determine if you've
attended the lectures. Again to
reiterate, attendance is mandatory and
we will track attendance to make sure
you have attended.
Now this is an interactive class. ask
you like questions. My theory is that
there's no such thing as a silly, wrong,
or embarrassing question. So, if you
have a question and you're feeling kind
of squeamish to ask, don't feel
squeamish because if you have that
question, the odds are
some hundred at least some hundred of
the 300 students in class also have the
same question. And so, if you ask them,
you're helping not just yourself, but
all of them. We'll try different tactics
to encourage interaction. For example,
calling out to students, please
participate.
Now, for in classroom lectures, we try a
few more tricks. We're going to assign
each of you a Pokemon name. This is your
secret ID for the class. During the
lectures, I'll call out random Pokemon
names and ask questions.
>> If it's your Pokemon, you must answer.
>> Hi, professor.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so I'm in the classroom. There's
like 15 people here and uh I just set up
the projection. So, they'll need a quick
hello. And
>> that's okay. We're still just going over
the uh logistics. So, uh maybe we can
just go over this bit later. Right.
And uh keep track of who's who's in
class
now. For Zoom classes, we're going to be
tracking Zoom chat and responses to make
sure that we answer all of your
questions and uh we keep the interaction
going.
Then last but not the least, this is a
dumb classroom, which means we expect
you to keep all of your devices shut
except the one that's watching this
lecture on Zoom. You're not you're not
supposed to be on Facebook, on anything
else, doing anything other than paying
attention to class. So in the classroom,
no phones, no laptops, nothing is open
except to answer polls or to view
lecture slides or take notes. So if we
find you using devices for any other
purpose, if you're in the class, I may
ask you to leave the classroom. On Zoom,
I'm trusting you. This is an honor.
And [clears throat] finally, I'm
handicapped. So, which means I'm
twisted. I have all kinds of problems. I
can't raise my arms. There are days on
which I can't walk. I run out of breath.
So, I have various ways of coping with
this. In class, sometimes my clipon mic
falls off. I ask my teachers to clip
them on. I use all kinds of strange
devices to point because they're light
because I can't raise my arm.
If you find these strange, please bear
with me because I have no choice in the
matter. So with that, I'll stop right
now and I'll pause for any questions
before we jump into the subject matter
of the course. Do we have any questions?
Any questions?
>> I was curious.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh I was curious just for clarification.
So we can use our laptop to take notes,
right?
>> If we're in person, laptop to take
notes, but you know, I might just walk
by you and make sure that that's all
you're doing. One of the things that
happens is that once I give one per
person permission to open their laptop,
>> it's very hard to resist the temptation
to go and sneak a peek at your email, to
go and sneak a peek at your Facebook or
whatever else. And it's not just you
who's distracted. You're distracting
everybody around you. And that becomes
an epidemic. The whole thing can
collapse. So, I try to keep that down.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> I have a question.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. You said we should have been added
to auto lab or something like that.
>> Yes.
>> But for me, I didn't receive any email
and even on canvas there is no
announcement about that. So,
>> so there's no canvas. You should just be
automatically added to autolab and
canvas. In principle, the both systems
should be getting the enrollment of uh
the SIO and just enrolling you. If you
find that you're not enrolled, please
make a post and RTS will take care of
it.
>> Okay. So, what about the study groups?
You said that we should sign up for the
study groups.
>> We have not already made a post with the
about the study groups. We will be
posting a form. you I encourage you guys
to form study groups on your own but you
must sign up and uh the form will allow
you to mention the entire study group.
Some of you will not actually have the
friends or be able to form groups on
your own. We'll make the groups for you.
We try to make sure that everybody has a
team to work with.
>> Okay.
So the classes should should be should
we be in the classroom for kegali
students for example? Now for the Zoom
classes, of course, you're going to be
attending on Zoom,
>> but for the inerson classes, the
classroom is has can only hold 140
people. So, everybody else has to be on
Zoom, but we expect you to be on Zoom
and keeping track and following the
class and we can check.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Any other questions?
Uh yeah, professor, I've not been
enrolled into the piaza. So, am I
expected to enroll myself or will I be
getting an invite?
>> You should be able to enroll yourself,
but if not, just email me or one of the
TAs and we'll enroll.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. All right. Any other questions?
No. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Love it again. So uh uh we have about
320 people enrolled in class as it
happens there are only 230 20 people or
230 people on zoom
>> which shows you what happens that people
stop attending they don't attend even at
the very beginning of the semester. This
can be bad because because the course
won't wait for you, right? So, we will
be checking attendance.
Anyway, let's start with the lecture.
So, today's lecture
uh we'll begin with a brief history of
neural networks. Under this, we will
discuss the roots of connectionism and
how it relates to cognition and the
brain. We'll contrast it to conventional
computer architectures. We will discuss
early models of neurons and neural
networks and their limitations. And then
we're going to close by introducing
modern neural networks and a discussion
of what they can compute. At any point
you may post questions on on the chat or
speak up and ask me questions.
So why are we in this course? Well,
artificial neural networks have now
become the main approach to AI. They
have been successfully applied to
various pattern recognition prediction
and analysis problems and in many of
these they have established the
state-of-the-art often beating
benchmarks set using earlier machine
machine learning techniques by very
large margins and in some cases in many
cases they have managed to solve
problems that you simply could not solve
using earlier methods.
So how did where are we now? How did all
of this happen?
We've been working on neural networks
for a very long time since the 1970s
actually much earlier as you'll see
shortly.
But the real breakthrough breakthroughs
that brought us to today [clears throat]
began happening in the 2010s with some
kind of a flashover in 2016. So let me
go through some of the breakthroughs in
2016.
This was a turning point. Researchers
had been working on automatic speech
recognition technology since the 1950s.
But after 60 years of research, the
state of automatic speech recognition in
2015 was pretty bad. You simply couldn't
use things like Siri, your typical
speech recognition system, made too many
mistakes to really be useful. Then in
mid 2016, we had this breakthrough. For
the first time, automatic speech
recognition systems outperformed human
beings on the switchboard task, which
consists of people calling up each other
on the phone and talking freely about
various topics. The breakthrough was
made possible by artificial neural
networks. And since then, the technology
has progressed in leaps and bounds, and
today SR systems generally outperform
humans in speech recognition on most
benchmarks. And speech recognition is
now a staple user interface. This
couldn't have happened without neural
networks.
Similarly, machine translation
after 40 years of research, empty
systems were horrible. In October 2016,
if you put an English sentence into
Google Translate, which was the best
translation system at the time,
translated it to Spanish and then
translated the Spanish back to English
again, what went in and what came out
wouldn't look anything like each other.
We used to we used to use this as a
party trick. It just didn't work. Then
in November 2016,
something amazing happened. Google
Translate suddenly became really good.
so good that even the professional
translators began using it for the first
pass of translation.
That's because in November 2016, Google
switched over to using neural networks
for translation.
The technology has continued to improve
and these days uh automatic machine
translation systems are better than all
but the most expert human translators
for most languages. And this was made
possible using neural networks
or uh the basic [clears throat] raw
intelligence. For the longest time, we
assumed that the ultimate challenge in
AI was playing mental games like chess
and go. And to the 1990s, automatics
chess games were horrible. They didn't
really do do very well. I don't know how
many of you know this but the first
chess game to beat a grandmaster was
built right here in CNU. This was a deep
thought by Feng Shingu and that was his
PhD cases. Then from there he went to
IBM where in 1995 he built the first uh
automatic chess game that beat a world
champion and after that no human has
really managed to beat the best computer
chess games. So yeah, we conquered
chess, but then we still had go
and go was was generally considered as
something that computers could never
really get good at. Go is vastly more
complex than chess. A chess game has 10
raised to 120 possible states, but Go
has 10 to 180 possible states. So it was
assumed a computer could never beat a
human. Then in 2016, Alph Go shocked the
world. could beat the world champion.
Today,
uh you have programs that don't even
need to know the rules and can begin
learning from scratch on their own and
in just a few hours they can learn to
play go and become good enough to be the
world champion. And this two is thanks
to deep neural networks. By the way,
someone just uh requested permission to
record I think using Otter. I denied it
because when I do that, when I allow per
when I grant permission, what happens is
that the actual recording of the class
that I've triggered on Zoom that
switches off sometimes and then we lose
the class recording. So, you might have
have to
uh bear with me on that.
So, here's another example. Image
captioning. This is also an old result
from 2016, but here for the first time,
computers could automatically caption an
image like a human. So, all of these
captions were automatically generated by
a neural network. Man in black shirt
playing a guitar. Construction worker in
orange safety vest working on a road.
Two young girls are playing with a Lego
toy. Boy doing backflip on the
wakeboard. Now, these are shockingly
accurate captions.
You might think it's kind of normal, but
it's not. And before 2016, something of
this kind was considered basically
impossible.
All of these were produced by a network
that only analyzed the image itself and
no other input. And this kind of
intelligence only became possible in
2016 thanks to neural networks. Of
course, modern models are far more
accurate. So, here uh this one, this is
a neural network model based AI system
that analyzed this picture taken by my
ex teaching assistant Current. He just
presented this picture. He took up his
room and asked Chad GPT about it. And
here are all the things it manages to
tell him. It tells him the ceiling in
the photo appears to have several
noticeable water stains which could
indicate potential water damage. It says
there are several posters of prints on
the wall featuring various images likely
of scenes from movies. It's true. The
room contains a few pieces of furniture
including a blue chair, a black
wardrobe, a storage unit, and a desk
with two monitors.
The ceiling has a light fixture and an
air vent suggesting this is a standard
room with typical building amenities.
The lower part of the photo photo shows
a bed with a person lying on it with
their foot visible in the foreground.
The bed has a comforter and some
clothing or linens on it. Uh the overall
condition the room appears somewhat
cluttered with personal belongings
spread out. Amazing. And this was just
done using a neural network. This was a
couple of years ago. These days they're
even smarter. So as you can see neural
networks are getting really, really,
really smart. And they are the solution
to so many problems from art to
astronomy to health, chemistry, physics,
biology, business management,
investment. They even prove mathematical
theorems. And so
basically neural networks can do
anything. If it's an AI task, the odds
are you cannot beat neural network
models. But what are these magical
neural networks? From where we stand at
this point in the course, they are just
these magical boxes where things go in
and other useful things come out. For
example, a voice recording goes in, its
transcription comes out. An image goes
in and its caption comes out. Maybe a
game state goes in and the next move
comes out. But what's in the box? To
understand this, let's begin here. All
of these tasks that we just looked at,
recognizing speech, captioning images,
playing complicated games, all of these
are fundamentally human activities
powered by human intelligence. So
perhaps the place to begin is with the
seat of all human intelligence, the
human brain or even earlier with our
amazing ability for cognition, our
ability to think, to analyze, to create.
So
maybe that's where we want to begin.
Understand how that happens. So here are
all the magical
cognitive capacities we've got. We can
learn. We can solve complex problems. We
can recognize patterns. We can create.
We can just sit in one spot and coach,
think and reflect and imagine and dream
without any external stimulus. So these
are the abilities that make us who we
are. So if we want to build a machine
with humanlike capabilities,
these are what we must emulate. But then
how exactly do we function? How does the
brain perform all of these activities?
The problem is that the brain is an
immensely complex organ. It has to be to
power our stupendous intelligence. So
anything less complex cannot generate
the kind of intelligence we have.
As a result, just quoting Marvin Minsky,
if the brain was simple enough to be
understood, we would be too simple to
understand it.
And
basically the complexity itself comes in
the way that generates intelligence
comes in the way of our ability to
understand it. Nonetheless, we're going
to try.
Now, people have been curious about
human cognition for thousands of years.
And in fact the earliest models for
cognition go back to at least the
ancient Greeks. The earliest known model
for human cognition is called
associationism.
And we know that theory goes back at
least to plateau in 400 BC. So this
picture here is the famous school of
Athens that you can find in the 16 in
the cyine chapel and this painting is by
Rafael. It shows all the scientific
grades from Greek times until the 15th
century. And here in the center you have
Plato and Ari Aristotle.
So Plate was the first to actually
record some kind of a theory for how
human brains work and this was
associationism.
Association in ism in fact remained the
primary model for human cognition for
from Plateau's time right until the
early 20th century with scientists like
David Hume and even uh as recently as
Ivan Pavlo developing theories around
it. Associationism posits that the
process of cognition is fundamentally
one of learning associations. So what
are associations?
These are literally percepts that we
somehow associated with one another to
make inferences. For example, in our
experience, we find that lightning is
generally followed by thunder. So we
make associations between lightning and
thunder and not just an association of
the events but also a temporal
association. So because usually
lightning is followed by thunder. When
you see a bolt of lightning, you expect
to hear hear thunder shortly.
Conversely, if you hear thunder, you
assume lightning has just struck
somewhere nearby. These are
associations.
And you're of course familiar with the
most famous association experiment of
all, Pavlo's dogs.
Now, where he showed that after enough
training, every time he rang a bell, the
dog drooled. There are many more slides
on associations in the slide deck.
Please look at them. I'm not presenting
them yet, but they'll appear in the
quiz.
So
we have this theory. We think through
the process of association and it's a
really good theory and we still use it
in machine learning implicitly. But then
the question is how and where are these
associations stored in our brain?
There were several sometimes strange
theories on how the brain actually
stores associations.
But things began to get more real once
we learned about the structure of the
brain itself. And this happened with the
invention of good microscopes
using which by the mid 1800s we had
figured out that the brain is
essentially a large mass of a special
kind of cell which we later call the
neurons. And these neurons are all
connected to to one another. Each neuron
has many neurons connecting into it and
each neuron in turn connects out to many
neurons. So the brain is essentially a
network of neurons and somehow this
network of neurons captures all of our
all of our capacity to be intelligent.
The first person to realize how things
worked in the brain was Alex Bane back
in the 1870s. Like all the scientists of
the day back then, Bane was a bit of
everything. He was a philosopher. He was
a psychologist. He was a mathematician.
He was a logician. He was a linguist.
Last but not the least, he was a
professor, which was much more difficult
to be back then than today. Now in his
1873 book mind and body
postulated that the brain stores
information through its connections he
he basically postulated that all of the
information that's stored in the brain
regarding associations between percepts
or more generally between stimulus and
response is captured through the
structure of the connections between
neurons. So this was in fact the first
connectionist model and he even came up
with various computational models for
for this theory. The key idea here is
one of his models. The key idea here was
that the same connections if
appropriately arranged could result in
different outputs for different inputs.
This may seem very obvious to us today
but in Bane's time 1873 it was
considered something really weird. So
here's one of the circuits here. Again,
we assume that all the inputs and all
outputs are binary either zero or one.
And a neuron fires if all of its inputs
fire. So here if A and B fire, X fires.
If B and C fire, Y fires. If A and C
fire, Z fires. So although you have a
single circuit for different input
patterns, you get different firing
patterns for the output.
And Bane even even included models where
a circuit's output could depend on the
intensity of the input. For instance,
over here, if the input is low
intensity, then X gets only two copies
of it and may not fire. But Y gets three
copies of it if the input persists long
enough and Y will fire. On the other
hand, if the input is high intensity,
both X and Y will fire. So these this
models like these are in fact very
modern neural network models. Bane came
up with them in 1873. over over 150
years ago. So these models have been out
around for that long. And Bane not only
showed the circuit structures, he also
proposed a learning mechanism whereby
the brain or any computational model of
the brain could learn these association,
these connections. And here's Bane's
proposed mechanism for how neural and
neuronal connections could be learned.
In his own words, when two impressions
concur or closely succeeded one another,
the nerve currents find some bridge or
place of continuity, better or worse,
according to the abundance abundance of
nerve matter available for the
transition. So this is literally Hebian
learning which you'll hear about in a
few minutes. Heb came up with a model in
the 1940s, but Bane theorized about them
almost 75 years before Donald.
That's how ahead of his time he was. And
being ahead of your times can often be a
bit of a curse. And so sadly, Bane's
peers in the 19th century thought he was
speaking nonsense. And eventually even
he began doubting himself. To quote
Bernard Bernard Russell, the fend of
fundamental cause of the trouble is that
in the modern world, the stupid are
cockure while the intelligent are full
of doubt. And so Bane doubted himself.
In 1873,
Bane postulated that there must be 1
million neurons and 5 billion
connections to capture 200,000 percepts.
This seemed like a very large number.
But then by 1883, he realized that this
had not taken into account the number of
partially formed associations. And to
account for these, he'd need even more
neurons and connections. So by 1903,
he decided that our brain was simply not
large enough, that his theory was wrong.
It would need too many neurons and too
many connections for his model to work.
And so he apologized and he recanted all
of his ideas which is which is a tragedy
because he was correct in 1873 and he
was wrong at the end. Our brain is very
large. It has 80 billion neurons and
about 100 trillion connections. That's
comfortably more than any capacity Bane
assumed was required. And his model is
in fact more or less how we think our
brain works today.
And so connectionism lives on. We know
by now that our brain is a connectionist
machine as predicted by Bane in 1873 and
David Fer in 1876.
Neurons connect to other neurons and the
processing and the information capacity
of the brain is a function of these
connections. And so modern artificial
neural networks are connectionist
machines which emulate the structure.
So this is what a connectionist machine
is. It's a network of simple processing
elements where all world knowledge about
the task the the machine performs is
stored in the connection between the
elements. The elements themselves are
very simple
and
modern neural networks are thus
connectionist machines consisting of
many little processing units that
connect to one another. Now uh
does does anybody remember what is the
type of architecture
that uh your standard processor has?
Does anybody remember the name of the
architecture? I'm sure you have some
computer science students over here who
remember this. Anybody?
It's a v oneman architecture.
>> So what is a oneman architecture?
Anyone?
Okay, someone answered but yeah,
>> so in a in the it's a variant of the
so-called one architecture in which you
have a processing unit and you have a
separate memory where programs and data
are stored.
There are other variants like you have
the Harvard architecture in which you
have separate memory for programs and
data and in the original one I mean
architecture you had this common memory
for both programs and data. Uh modern
machines use a hybrid approach. The
processor is Harvard architecture but
the main memory is the one I'm in now
Princeton architecture. Now those
differences are not important. What is
important for us is the form of the
architecture itself. your processor is
separated from the memory which holds
the programs and the data. So if you
want to run a new program, all you have
to do is to upload a new program into
the memory and you're set to go. Which
is why your typical computer or even
your phone is able to do so many
different things. In order to make it
perform a new task, you just have to
load the corresponding program into the
memory and you're set to go. That's not
the case with connectionist machines.
for connectionist machines because the
program is in the connections. The
computer itself is the program. The
program and its memory are all encoded
in the connections between the units. To
change the program, you have to change
the machine itself. Which is why you
don't you very rarely build hardware
neural networks with everything built in
because if you wanted to change the
program, you'd have to build something
completely new. Instead, we typically
emulate the connectionist machine on
regular Harvard and Princeton
architecture machines.
And so
to recap, neural network based AI has
taken over most AI tasks. Neural
networks originally began as
computational models of the brain or
more more generally as models of
cognition. The earliest model of
cognition was associationism. The more
recent model is connectionist. Neurons
connect to neurons and the workings of
the brain are encoded in these
connections and current neural network
models are connectionist machines. So we
now have our first poll.
Uh let's see.
Can you folks see the poll?
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
And listen, the slides must be on the
course website. Okay, let me end the
poll.
And does anybody want to answer the
first question? What's the answer?
>> Alexander,
>> that's B, right? And for the second
question, how many connections did we
say exist between neurons of the brain?
>> 80 billion.
>> 100 trillion. Right? The correct answer
here is 100 trillion.
So uh uh Alex Bane was the first person
who proposed connectionism
and the human brain has about 100
trillion connections which is what makes
it so powerful. And so here's where we
are. Connectionist machines are networks
of processing elements.
All the information the machine uses to
perform its computation is in the
connections. But what are these
individual elements themselves?
To understand that, let's go back to the
brain. The individual units in the brain
are neurons. A neuron looks roughly like
this. It has a head called the soma
within which the nucleus resides. The
soma has several dendrites through which
it receives signals from other neurons.
The neurons the a neuron generates
signals that are spiked trains and the
rate of the spike train depends on the
accumulated signal from the other
neurons. At a high level, we can think
of it in this simple way. If the total
input signal from all the other neurons
exceeds a threshold, this neuron fires.
That output signal then then travels
down this long leg called the axon from
which it's transmitted to other neurons.
Now, here's an interesting factoid. This
axon is very long. And so, it has to be
protected for the neuron to work. and
it's covered for protection. It's
covered with a sheet sheet of fat called
the myin sheath. This fat is crucial for
the functioning of the brain. In fact,
scientists who studied this sort of
thing have found that the key
distinction between Einstein's brain and
normal brains was not that he had more
neurons in his head, that he had more
gal cells, the cells that produce the
smile, the sheath that protects the
axon, than normal people. So it appears
that the more fat you have in your head,
the smarter you are. And in fact, being
called a fathead is actually a
compliment. Now, here's another factoid
that may only interest me. It should
interest you also. Neurons don't undergo
cell division. Why? Because all the
information in the brain lies in the
connection between neurons. If the
neuron divided, these connections would
get destroyed and you'd lose that
information. So a neuron once it's in
place cannot divide.
New neurons instead are created from
neural stem cells and neurogenesis
which is the formation of new neurons
begins to slow down almost as soon as
you're born and pretty soon goes down to
something close to zero. In other words,
you're born with almost all the brain
you'll ever have. Anyway, for our
computational connectionist models too,
our compute units are going to emulate
the nature of this biological neuron.
And the first computational model for
the neuron was proposed by these two
guys, Melo and Pitts. Warren Melo was a
neuro physiologist in the University of
Chicago. Walter Pittz was a homeless guy
who just turned up and knocked on his
door. So I'll let you figure out which
of these is Walter Pitts and which of
these is Melo. Who do you think is Pitts
over here? The guy to the left or the
right? Anyone?
Nobody want to take a guess?
Right. So this hobo looking
the hobo looking guy over here is
actually Warren Mccelo and Walter Pittz
was a very young guy. He was only 20
when he knocked on melo door. He was a
runaway from run away from home and he
stayed with melo for a few months and
they came up with this amazing model
called the mechlo and pits model of the
neuron. It was published in 1943 in this
paper a logical calculus of ideas
imminent in nervous activity in the
bulletin of mathematical biohysics
physics. So this picture on top is a
pictorial visualization of the model.
Now their model was a breakthrough. how
it was the first computational model for
a biological process, namely the neuron.
And so here is where began the entire
science of modeling biological elements
through mathematical models. In their
model, they modeled the neurons in the
brain as performing propositional logic,
basically boolean logic.
And so by modeling it as performing
propositional logic, they suddenly give
us attractable mathematical formalism to
represent the brain's operations.
This is a little more detailed picture.
So the actual neuron itself is shown by
the triangle. The line going out
represents the outgoing signal. The
colored lines represent incoming signals
from other neurons which connect to this
neuron through these synaptic
connections. There are two types of sap
synapses. The excitatory sinapsis shown
in green and the inhibitory sinapse
shown in red. The excitatory sinapse
transmits signals weighted signals from
other neurons to this neuron. So the
number of connections over here
represents the weight. Now this causes
the neuron to trigger and fire. But if
there's any signal coming up the
inhibitory connection then this
absolutely prevents the neuron from
firing regardless of what is coming in
through the excitatory signal. If the
inhibitory input is turned on the output
of the neuron will always be turned on.
But now
by appropriate choice of excitatory and
inhibitory synapses the mecho and pitch
neuron can be made to emulate any
boolean gate. So these are shown here.
In each case, the neuron shown by this
triangle here fires if the total input
is at least two. So in the top left, if
neuron one fires, then one time unit
later, neuron 2 gets two inputs and so
it fires.
Over here,
this neuron responds to one and two. If
this were a boolean function, what is
this boolean function? Can anybody tell
me what is this boolean function?
This one here. It's an and. Both one and
two have to fire. That's when three
receives two inputs. What about this
guy? Yeah.
What is this?
>> Why?
>> That's an R because if either one or two
fire, three receives two inputs and so
the neuron fires. And this is a little
more complex. one and not two because if
two fires two is inhibitory, right? And
so you can see that
you can construct pretty much any
boolean gate using the perceptron and so
you can construct any boolean circuit
using these neurons but you can do a
whole lot more. Meal and pits also
showed that you can produce complex
responses. For example, there's a very
well-known phenomenon in human
perception. If you touch something cold
very briefly, just touch it and take
your finger off, it doesn't feel cold,
it feels hot. But if you keep your
finger on it for a little longer, then
you will feel the cold. This is well
known. And they showed that you can
actually model this using the structure.
Here I have two inputs, neurons one and
two. And these are a heat receptor and a
cold receptor. This blue unit is just a
delay unit.
It basically reflects whatever the cold
receptor got but one time unit later.
Now unit four is the cold response. Unit
three is the heat response. At the
initial time all outputs are zero. Now
if the cold receptor fires at say time
t= 1 then one time instant later the
cold response unit cold sensation unit
gets one signal from two. But then if
you're if you touch the coal receptor
very briefly then one time second later
this guy this guy gets a signal but at
that time this has not fired. So you're
not going to feel the cold but if you
keep touching the cold
object for a long time at time one this
sends something down. At time two also
this sends something down to the cold
center cold cold sensor. Now this guy
reflects because it's a delayed version
of two. It reflects what it's what the
cold receptor saw one time instant ago.
And so if the coal receptor sees
perceives coal for two continuous time
instance then the cold sensation neuron
gets two inputs and it fires. On the
other hand if you just touch the coal
sensor for only one time unit then this
at the first you know this guy gets one
input one time instant later. It gets
one input two time instance later.
Neither is enough for this to fire. But
then what happens here?
If you just touch it for one time
instant, one time second instant later,
this fires. Another time instant later,
this fires and then eventually this
fire. So you feel heat. But if you keep
touching the cold object for an extended
period of time,
then at the second time instant, this
inhibitory signal comes in and prevents
this guy from firing. And so the heat
sensor doesn't go off. And so you have
this model which captures this human
phenomena that a brief touch of cold
makes you feel heat but if you keep if
you're persistent
uh uh input of the cold sense to the
cold scepter
will actually make you feel cold.
So clearly
you can see that this meal model is
quite powerful but then it had a lot
they faced a lot of criticism. First,
they claimed that the network could
compute a small class of functions. This
is true. They claimed that if you
provide the network with tapes, they
would become Turing complete. That they
could solve any problem that a Turing
machine could solve. Also true if you
don't consider the size of the machine.
But they didn't actually prove several
of their results. These were just
claims. And most importantly, they
didn't provide any learning mechanism
whereby the network could learn its
connection weights from experience from
data. For that we had for to wait for
another guy. This guy Donald Heb who I
mentioned a little while ago.
Now Heb was another interesting
character. He was a Canadian. He
initially trained to be a novelist. Then
he decided what he really wanted to do
was to be a farmer. Then he threw that
away and decided to become a hobo. Then
he figured he'd be a school teacher. And
then he said, you know, screw it. No,
no, this is working for me. And so he
went and joined Harvard and became he
became a psychologist and got a PhD PhD
from Harvard and then went on to work in
a variety of places. So in 1949
he published a book called organization
of behavior where he outlined a
mechanism whereby neuron and neuronal
cells in the brain could learn their
connection with experience from data. So
here's how we describe the mechanism.
When an axon of cell A is near enough to
excite a cell B and repeatedly or
persistently takes part in firing it,
some growth process or metabolic change
takes place in one or both cells such
that A's efficiency as one of the cells
firing B is increased. Sounds complex
but basically what he's saying is that
if A connects to B and A repeatedly
excites B, then its ability to excite B
becomes stronger. So very pivily it's
often stated as neurons that fire
together wire together. Now here's how
it actually works.
Let's look at one connection between two
neurons. Let's call them X and Y. Now
neuron X connects to neuron Y at a
sinapse. At the sinapse, the axonal
connection from neuron X has a knob
called the synaptic knob. And the two
neurons don't actually touch one
another. What happens is that uh when a
signal comes down this neuron, some
chemicals called neurotransmitters are
are emitted from this head which go and
trigger the second neuron which gets its
input.
Now, every time a signal from X
successfully triggers the the the second
neuron Y, then this head gets a teeny
weeny bit larger, which means that the
next time around a signal comes down
from here, it becomes easier for this
head to trigger B. So, anytime one
neuron excites another successfully, it
makes it easier for the neuron to excite
the second neuron the next time. Now,
this can be formulated in that
Let wxy be the weight of the connection
between neuron x and neuron y. In this
model, neurons are binary and the output
is either zero or one representing
whether the neuron is firing or not. So
the heavy learning rule says that at any
time both x and y take the value one
meaning neuron x is successfully
triggered neuron y wxy the weight of the
connection increases. So you can write
it in math as wxy
= wxy + beta * xy. See that this
increment note that this increment only
happens if both an x and y take the
value one. So if a neuron successfully
triggers another neuron the weight of
the connection increases. This simple
formula called the heavian learning rule
is actually the basis of many learning
rules in machine learning. But then
there's something problematic with this.
Can anybody identify what the problem is
is over here? Anyone? What's the problem
with it with with this with this
formula?
Anybody?
>> Looks like linear infinite growth.
>> It's infinite growth. There's no
negative learning. It keeps increasing
and increasing and increasing. So, it's
fundamentally unstable, right? The
weights can only increase and never
decrease. So over time eventually all
the weights will become large and the
entire model is going to become useless.
And people came up with various
proposals like uh Sanger's rule and
whatnot to try to make uh to try to sort
of correct this and make this work in a
more uh reasonable way. But the best and
the most lasting update to the Hebian
rule came came with the introduction of
a new model. But before that I just
released my next poll.
And
then we'll go back to the improvement to
He's
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
All right,
let me end the poll. So pretty much all
of you got the answer right. But does
anybody want to tell me what the answer
is over here?
>> It's unstable because there's no
reduction in weights.
>> Exactly.
And so we need an improvement to this
model. And that improvement was proposed
by this guy Frank Rosenblot. He was a
psychologist and logician at Yale. And
uh he actually is the father of modern
neural networks. He died at the age of
40 unfortunately in a boating accident
where he went boating to celebrate his
40th birthday. Anyway, uh he in 1958 he
proposed a model called the perceptron
which at that time he was sure would
solve all AI problems. Here's the full
picture of Rosenbl's perceptron. It's
actually a very complex structure
composed of many units arranged in many
layers with epherent and apherent and
epherent connections and whatnot. But
then here's a simpler visualization
which captures its essence. So
Rosenlot's original proposal related to
perception in the eye and uh so the
details of it are in the slides but in
the simplified the simplified
visualization
uh is something like this. These over
here are the sensory units. These would
be the cells in your retina. Then you
have something called an association
layer with many associative units which
consists of many neurons each of which
connects to the sensory units. And then
finally you have a layer of response
units and these response units connect
to all of the associated units.
And this entire structure is what
Rosenblot called the perceptron. In
modern parliament when we speak you know
these days when I speak of a perceptron
I'm only speaking of uh say this one guy
over here each of these individual units
is what we would call a perceptron but
when Rosenl first introduced this he
called this whole thing was called a
perceptron
anyway let's see what each of these
units looks like just this one guy how
does it uh uh what does it look like
So here that unit looks something like
this. Each neuron receives a number of
inputs x1 through xn. Corresponding to
each input is a weight wn. It computes a
weighted sum of all of these inputs. And
the weights can be either positive or
negative. If the weighted sum exceeds
some threshold t, the neuron outputs a
one otherwise it outputs a zero. So in
equations we can write it like so.
If the weighted sum minus the threshold
is positive then the neuron outputs a
one otherwise it outputs a zero.
So electrical engineers will recognize
this unit as a threat as threshold logic
performing threshold logic.
Rosenblad also provided a beautiful
learning algorithm for how these units
could learn their weights.
And so here let w be the weight with
which any input x
uh is connected to a perceptron. After
each new input the weight is adjusted to
account for the error between the actual
output of the perceptron and the desired
output of the perceptron. So in math we
can write it as w = w + a * d - y d of x
- y of x * x where where y of x is the
actual output of the perceptron and d of
x is the desired output of the
perceptron. Does anybody see the
similarity between this thing and and
the the heavian rule?
Do you see the similarity between this
and the heavy rule? How does it differ
from the heavian rule? anyone.
>> It has a loss function so to speak.
>> It has a loss function gives negative
feedback. Here's the thing in
rule. This guy was just y
which which increasing and increasing
and increasing. Here you introduce the
notion of a desired output and if the
output is already equal to the desired
output the weight does not change. It
changes not in proportion to the desired
output but in proportion to the error
from the desired output. That was the
critical difference between this and the
original Hebian rule. And so this
Rosenlot not only came up with this
idea, it's a beautiful learning rule and
he also showed that if you have linearly
separable data, meaning the data for
which uh if you have data for which the
desired Y is one and other data for
which the desired Y is zero and these
data can be separated by a hyper plane.
Then this learning rule will is
guaranteed to converge to give you a set
of weights that will separate the two
sets of logs.
We'll talk about more about this later.
Right now, Rosenblot originally assumed
correctly that with the appropriate
choice choice of weights and a large
enough number of units, this full model
could represent any boolean function and
perform any logic and the popular media
of the time bought into the hype. So,
here are some snippets from a couple of
newspapers at that time back in the 50s.
The embryo of an electronic computer
that the Navy expects will be able to
walk, talk, see, write, reproduce
itself, and be conscious of its
existence. 1958.
Frankenstein monster designed by the
Navy that paints. 1958. Now, I mean,
we're getting there, but in 1958, we
were 70 years away. And that wasn't just
it. The problem was Rosenblat made
claims about this model.
But by and by people began assuming that
the claim also held true for the
individual units in the model which are
these guys right and that these guys
themselves were what we'd call universal
boolean machines that could compute any
boolean function. No, this is not true.
And as a result of this exaggeration, as
a result of this exaggeration, research
funding in neural networks dried up for
a decade and uh research almost came to
a standstill. But for now, let's look at
the capabilities of this individual
unit, what is now called a perceptron.
In fact, even the simple unit is very
powerful. It's relatively easy to see
how this perceptron can mimic any
boolean function. Consider these
examples here in the circle. uh I have a
threshold and the numbers above the
arrows represent the weight. So if the
total weighted input matches the
threshold the neuron will fire. What is
this gate over here? Anybody?
What is this function here? Top land.
>> And what about this one here?
or
>> or and this guy
>> not
>> that's a not if x is one the input
becomes minus one and it fires but if x
is zero
you know if x is one and it doesn't fire
but if the x is zero it fires right so
this is a n so you can see you can model
any boolean gate and and but then
the limitation of the individual units
becomes apparent when we consider the
exort there's no setting of the weights
for which the unit can compute X or Y
and we'll see why later right so in any
case this means the perceptron is not a
universal machine boolean machine how do
you resolve this to resolve this we go
back to the brain the brain is not just
a single neuron it's a large network of
neurons so for our computational model
too the individual neurons perceptrons
are weak they are not enough but you can
greatly extend them to do what you want
once you begin networking many of them.
And so if you just connect up three of
these perceptrons like this, we can
compute an XR. Here we have connect
connected three perceptrons in a layered
manner. This top one connect computes X
or Y. This computes not X or not Y. This
ends the two. And so now you have the X
order, right? Some terminology over
here. These two neurons, we call them
the hidden layer. Not because they're
really hidden, but we because we are not
really interested in the individual
outputs. We are interested in the output
of this final neuron which we call the
output neuron or the neurons in this
layer called the output layer. Anyway,
so once you realize that you can begin
connecting up uh perceptrons into a
network to compute more complex boolean
functions, then you realize you can
compute arbitrarily complex boolean
functions simply by connecting up
perceptrons in the right way. And so in
cognitive terms, we can compute
arbitrary boolean functions of sensory
input. So for example, this network here
computes this crazy function of four
inputs.
It doesn't matter what kind of boolean
function you give me. I can always
construct a network [clears throat] that
computes of perceptrons that computes
that boolean function. And so
a multi-layer perceptron, this is what
we will call a multi-layer perceptron
because you've connected up the
perceptrons in layers. They're actually
a universal boolean function.
So story so far, neural networks began
as computational models for the brain.
They're connectionist machines. They
comprise networks of neural units. The
mecho and pits model had neurons as
boolean threshold units which models the
brain as performing propositional logic.
They gave learning rule. Heb came up
with a learning rule. Neurons that fire
together wire together or it was
unstable. Rosenlot's perceptron which is
a variant of the mechoic neuron had a
provably convergent learning rule but
the individual elements in it are
limited in their capacity but
multi-layer perceptrons can model
arbitrarily complex boolean functions
they are what are called universal
boolean functions
but then our brain is not boolean
everything we've discussed so far is
about boolean inputs and outputs our
brain operates on real valued inputs and
often makes real valued or nonv boolean
inferences. So how does the perceptron
square this?
First let's consider real valued inputs.
Again the weights two are real valued.
The perceptron fires if the weighted sum
of inputs exceeds the threshold t by
fires it may say the output is one
otherwise the output is zero. So this is
your perceptron. I can redraw it
slightly like so. Instead of having a
threshold t over here, I can say the
perceptron first computes an aphine
function of the inputs which is a
weighted sum of the inputs plus a bias
term and then it passes this aphine
value through an activation threshold
function which fires if this value
coming in is positive and does not fire
outputs a zero otherwise. So can you see
how these two are the same model with
just a small change in terminology?
Can can you can you guys see that these
two are the same thing? Yes or no?
Anyone guys it's awfully quiet.
There's just one person who sees that
they are the same thing. So what is the
confusion here?
Right. So instead of saying I'm going to
be applying
saying the weighted sum might should be
greater than the threshold I can say I
computed a weighted sum plus a bias
where the b here is minus t right and
then I put it through a threshold
activation the the bias term basically
represents this threshold Jeffrey
that answer you
this minus t and this plus b are the
same
that answer there's a question on in the
chat.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's the one. What does
the bias term represent? Right?
That's the one I'm talking about. So
this bias
this, look at this here. I'm saying
summation wxus t that's summation wx
plus z. So this is the threshold.
Anyways,
so this is an aphine function of the
input. Does anybody know the difference
between aphine and linear? What's that?
What's the difference
between Afine and Lia?
Anyone?
>> Um,
>> what's the difference?
>> Aine Aine is not reversible.
>> Anybody else? Non- negative. Okay. So
suppose I have a bunch of inputs and I
say some and I call the summation wixi.
If I equate this to zero, this
represents the equation of a hyper plane
that goes through origin. If all the
inputs are zero, then this becomes zero.
This is a linear function.
On the other hand, if I have summation
wi xi
+ b,
if I equate this to zero, this
represents the equation of a hyper
plane.
It's still a hyper plane but it no
longer goes through necessarily goes
through origin. So this is an aphine
function. You see the difference between
the two
linear versus aphine.
Yes or no?
Right? Okay. And so
you first compute an aine function of
the input and then put it through a
threshold activation. And once you
realize you can put it through a
threshold activation then you can which
generates outputs of either zero or one.
You can have other activations functions
and uh this
uh
allows the output to be real valued
rather than binary.
But in any case for the purpose of
building our intuition and
interpretability I'll continue to assume
the threshold activation for now. So
here's the real value perceptron again.
It operates on a real valued space of
inputs. If the weighted sum of the
inputs exceeds a threshold, the output
is one. Otherwise, it's a zero. And the
boundary between the two is where the
weighted sum exactly equals a threshold.
And so that is going to be a hyper
plane. So the overall function is a
heavy side function of this kind.
There's a boundary. On one side of the
boundary, the output is zero. On the
other side, the output is one.
So is everybody seeing this how this is
true? Yes or no?
This make sense to you guys? Okay. So
once you realize this
then you can see
model boolean functions. When the input
is boolean then if you have two inputs
the two inputs can take values 0 0 1 1
or 1 0. I can always design my weights
such that this boundary lies here. If
this boundary lies here, what is the
function I've captured over here? What
is the boolean function
>> over here? Anyone?
>> Or
>> or?
>> That's an or right.
>> What is so if I put the boundary here,
what is the boolean function?
>> And
>> that's an and if I put the boundary over
here, what's the boolean function?
not
>> that's a not right and so now can you
tell me why you cannot do an exor
I'll let you think about it we'll look
at this in the next class right
and so but now once you see how a single
perceptron behaves you can immediately
see how to network them to construct
arbitrarily complex decision boundaries
for example if I want a network that
looks at two-dimensional inputs but
produces a one Only if the input is in
this pentagon and zero outside. Here's
what I would do. I'd have one perceptron
that captures this boundary. It outputs
a one in the yellow region and a zero in
the zero. Zero outside. Another
perceptron for this boundary. A third
perceptron for this boundary. A fourth
perceptron for this boundary. And a
fifth perceptron for this boundary. And
the pentagon is the only region in which
all five of them have the output value
one. So I can have a final perceptron
which just compares the weighted sum to
five. And this network is now going to
output a one if the input is inside the
pentagon and zero zero outside. So you
managed to capture this pentagon. But
once you know how you can how to
construct
uh a network or a pentagonal decision
region, you can make networks for more
complex regions like this double
pentagon. We want the network to output
a one if the input is inside either of
these pentagons and zero zero outside.
So you can have one subnet which outputs
a one inside this lower pentagon,
another one which outputs a one inside
this upper pentagon and a final neuron
ors the two. And so now this o overall
network is going to output a one if the
input is in either of these two
pentagons and zero outside.
Is this making sense to you guys?
This picture?
Yes. No.
So
okay.
once you know how to do this, you can do
more crazy decision boundaries like
this, right? Can be arbitrarily complex.
And so
uh you know we know now we know how to
build multi-layer perceptrons for
complex classification tasks. Your
inputs are now high dimensional. For
example, if you if you were building a
network to recognize digit two in the
eminest digits, your inputs are
784dimensional,
the region of the input space that
corresponds to the digit two will have
some shape. Maybe like this peanut here.
And so all you need to do is to build an
NLP that fires that outputs a one if the
input is in this region and zero
outside. And so you have a classifier.
And so here's the story so far. MLPS are
connectionless computational models.
Individual perceptrons are computational
equivalents of neurons. The MLP is a
layered composition of many perceptrons.
They can model any boolean function
because individual perceptrons act as
act as boolean gates and networks are of
perceptrons are boolean functions. So
MLPS are universal boolean functions.
MLPS can also model any decision
boundary because individual perceptrons
capture linear boundaries and complex
boundaries can be composed from these
linear boundaries. So MLPS can represent
arbitrary decision boundaries which
means they can be used to classify data.
So MLPS are universal classifiers.
Uh here is your third poll.
I'll give you only 30 seconds for this
because I have some to go in class. I
have five minutes left.
Okay, 5 seconds, guys.
Let me end this part. So can anybody
answer how many will be need?
>> Seven.
>> Seven. Right. Six for the sides. Six
sides
and the seventh to them all. Right.
Perfect.
So that was that was for
you know boolean outputs with boolean or
real inputs. But then what if the output
is continuous valued?
How can we build a network for this? To
see how this can be done, I'm going to
consider a function of a scalar input.
The input X is scalar. The output is
also scalar. Now I can compose the
simple net. The upper perceptron fires
if the input exceeds threshold t1. The
lower and lower lower one fires if it
exceeds t2. So if I combine the two with
weight one and minus1 respectively. Then
as the input goes from minus infinity
infinity to plus infinity. When it
crosses t1 this guy fires
but until it crosses t2 this doesn't
fire. Right? So between t1 and t2 the
output is one. But once the input
exceeds T2, they cancel each other out.
So this network produces a one when the
input lies between T1 and T2.
And once I can build that, then if I
have a function of this kind, I can
always approximate this function in this
pie-wise linear manner. And so I can
have pairs of neurons for every little
bar, scale their output by the height of
that function within the bar and sum
them up. And that's going to give me a
pretty good approximation for this
continuous value function. And I can
make this function approximation
arbitrarily precise by simply making
these bars narrower and narrower. That
make sense?
Does this did this approximation make
sense?
Yes or no?
I have like one one yes. What about the
rest of you guys?
It's easy, right? And so
I'll skip this poll, right? The story so
far we've done, we've seen that MLPS are
connectionist computational models and
they're classification engines, but we
just added to the story that they can
also model continuous valued functions.
And so MLPS can do a whole lot of other
things. They can uh model memory. They
can per they can model probability dist
using uh neoly networks. They can model
probability distributions over real
complex and integer domains. They can
model a posteriority and a priority
probability distributions of data. They
can even generate data from complicated
or unknown probability distributions. So
from the AI perspective, the neural
network is just a function given one or
more inputs. It computes the function to
predict one or more outputs.
Going back to the beginning of class, in
all of these tasks which we saw early in
the lecture, these boxes are just
functions. They take an input and
produce an output. So the voice
recognition system, for example, takes
in voice and produces a transcription.
The image captioner takes an image, it
produces a caption. The game playing
machine, it takes in a game state, it
outputs the next move. So these are all
just functions. And so when we do it
with neural networks, all of these
functions are modeled or approximated by
neural networks. And so that's how we
perform AI using neural networks. And so
to the to to complete the story so far,
interesting AI tasks are functions that
can be modeled by the neural network.
And so [clears throat] in today's class,
we've gone through a brief history of
neural networks of connectionism. We've
seen some early models and their
limitations. We've introduced modern
neural networks and what they can
compute.
And so here's where we are. MLPS can
basically model any kind of
computational task. They are universal
approximators.
But then
there's more to it than that. And in the
next lecture, we'll talk more about MLPS
as universal approximators and the issue
of depth in neural networks. So I'll
stop here right on the dot and I can
take questions.